<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Justin Kropp</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2017-09-11T17:35:44-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Mark Otto</name>
   <email>justinkropp@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>What Is A Designer</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/24/what-is-a-designer/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/24/what-is-a-designer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been re-reading Norman Potter’s eloquent What is a designer. There are a handful of books that I revisit periodically to both refresh my perspective on and rekindle the relationship with my discipline — graphic design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of this book has proven to be, with each passing year, more and more imperative as a tool for young designers to use in exploring and shaping their discipline. Potter positions design as a serious act of intellectual enquiry. The following passages always resonate with me in a profound way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-design-education-principles&quot;&gt;On design education principles:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The reality factors in academic life may appear to derive less from studio project work, which is always imperfectly ‘real’, than from the discussion that surrounds such work, the exploration of angles of attack, and the slow take-up represented by the experience of community.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Design education must, by its nature, dig below the surface, and must at the outset be more concerned to clarify intentions than to get good results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-good-design&quot;&gt;On good design:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For the designer, good design is the generous and pertinent response to the full context of a design opportunity, whether large or small, and the quality of the outcome resides in a close and truthful correspondence  between form and meaning. The meaning of a good garden spade is seen in its behavior, that it performs well; in its look and feel, its strength and required durability; in a directness of address through the simple expression of its function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last bit — &lt;em&gt;a directness of address through the simple expression of its function&lt;/em&gt;. So good. Adhering to this as a consistent and applied principle of digital product design could alleviate much of the ubiquity of atrocious user experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Alone At My Desk</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/20/alone-at-my-desk/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/20/alone-at-my-desk</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a lot of time thinking about design as both a discipline and a practice. The former reinforcing the latter and vice versa. I try to engage in each daily — exercising the discipline to move the practice forward. To evolve. To get better. And with any worthy pursuit, failure is part of it. But the sticky part is that failure comes only after trying. Never before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failure is difficult to deal with, but I keep trying to move my practice forward because the rewards are usually worth it, the process is usually enjoyable – albeit a tinge sadistic – and it is my professional responsibility as a design practitioner. Were that drive to push forward fade away, I could no longer respectfully call myself a graphic designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing, being a core component in the discipline, requires just as much practice. But I fall short here. Writing is torture for me. My confidence wanes as soon as I sit down to write. I’m familiar with and comfortable navigating through the tools of graphic design: typography, color, composition, form, etc. Words are a primary tool set of writing, but they’re slippery to me. Elusive. I’ve yet to dedicate a lot of time to their exploration. This part of my discipline is lacking. I’d like to change that. I need to change that if I wish to continue to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a blog in the past, but more often than not it simply served as an annual opportunity to redesign, rather than an ongoing vehicle for exploratory discourse. So, with that, here’s to giving myself yet another opportunity to change that behavior and get some words down — consistently. No promises that I won’t slip, but I’ll do my best to get up and keep going. If you happen to find anything here valuable or something resonates with you, I’d love to hear about it. If you see an error, or just want to give me a bit of feedback or advice, I welcome that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s to a well honed tool set.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Discourse, Joe Stewart</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/09/joe-stewart/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/09/joe-stewart</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Work &amp;amp; Co&lt;/a&gt; has built up an already impressive list of accomplishments — everything from the company leadership, to the culture, to the body of work. What are you most proud of so far?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s very nice of you to say. I’m most proud of some very, very basic things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the work we’re doing is good, and I believe in it.
I like where I work, and I think my co-workers do too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it seems too simple, but the goal of this project was really just to make good work, and make it with people we like in an environment we like. That was really it. The name “Work &amp;amp; Co” is just that - the two things that matter. The work you make and the company you keep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels nice. I really do feel proud of the company. I guess I’ve never thought about that, but ya - I’m just proud that the idea worked and we’re all really happy. It’s silly to say – but – I love that. The partners at Work &amp;amp; Co and I  all feel good about what we’ve been able to do so far and how good it feels to stick to your guns and go for it and have it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also have to say I’m very proud of the integrity we have shown as a company to only work on the things we really care about. We really love digital product design and think it’s important (and fun to work on). That’s all we do – just focus on digital product design. At times, it can be hard to say no to some opportunities that come your way that could grow our business, or whatever – but – in the end I’m really proud that we all simply agree upon what’s important to us, and that really is those two simple things. Work. Company. I really love that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conversely, is there something you can now say you would have done differently?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think one thing that was a little hard in the beginning was that from day 1, Work &amp;amp; Co was on two coasts. I was on the west coast, and everyone else was on the east coast. I really (selfishly) wanted to move back to the west coast. I have two little boys, and it’s hard to do that in Brooklyn, so I moved to Portland right when the company started. This probably made things much harder than they needed to be… and I think I owe the NY guys a few beers over it, but – it’s all worked out. We now have about 80 people in New York, 20 in Portland, and another 20 in Rio. It worked out in the end, but it was a bit of a learning experience in terms of starting a company across multiple offices from day one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work &amp;amp; Co only makes digital products and services, yet the philosophy seems to give a pretty distinct nod to traditional principles of graphic design: type, form, play, wit. How important is it that these critical elements of our discipline remain elevated in the work you produce?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad you brought this up. So – all of us working in digital right now are the first generation of digital designers. We’re making the rules as we go. There are no greats to look up to or masters to study. It’s very hard to find inspiration in digital design, considering there isn’t much history there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Work &amp;amp; Co, all of us really go to the past - to other mediums to try to see how those before us solved problems. You bring up traditional graphic design in your question, and that’s a big one for us. There is so much to learn from what happened in print before our time to solve the same problems we face today. For example - today we have to design a website with 10 stories above the fold. Well, guess what - they literally had to do that too when designing newspapers, so - go study that. You’ll find your answer. Digital design is 99% type and grid. If you can nail type and grid, you’re gold. So, we study the masters of type and grid religiously, and all of them worked in more traditional media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also very very inspired by industrial design. Our job is to make tools… digital tools, but – it does the same thing. If we do our job very well, you will like using that tool. This is most often experienced in industrial design. Having a favorite knife because you love the way it feels, or the thought that went into it. Using certain pencils because they fit the best in your hand. Enjoying pressing the button on your coffee grinder… that’s a weird thing to like, but we all have these little things in life that we love to use. These things are what we strive for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, because there really isn’t much of this very high design for digital yet, we study the past to try to design for today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Similarly, how important is it, as a designer, to remain close to and understand the work of design pioneers, like Saville, Vignelli, and Rams to name just one — those that truly helped shape our discipline?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me it’s number one. This is the start. You have to know where this stuff came from. You have to understand what worked: How did these guys make it work? What was different about the way they thought or designed or practiced or approached that somehow made their work better than everyone else’s? So much of design is just reshuffling of existing ideas – and – to not know where the idea started from is very limiting to a designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really similar to music. You can hear a song now and know that this band is just ripping off another band, and you’re better off listening to the original. Chances are the original guys probably had a much better album because they knew what they were doing. Same with design. If you look at the album covers before &lt;a href=&quot;https://designmuseum.org/designers/peter-saville&quot;&gt;Saville&lt;/a&gt;, and the album covers that came after Saville… well… you know what I think: just study Saville.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you find that their work is still able to inspire day after day despite a growing artificial patina vying for our affection? I suppose what I’m asking is: can the digital design work of today possess soul? An ethos?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think their work - the people you mentioned (Saville, Vignelli, Rams) - is still able to inspire day after day and forever. It will never stop. It’s in the pantheon. These people produced some of the best design the world has ever seen. To me, this is like asking if the statue of David is still inspiring even though it’s old. There are very few people working at this level now, and I don’t think any of them are working in digital. I don’t think digital, as a medium, is there yet. It’s not mature enough to ‘possess a soul’ as you say. It’s just too early. It will get there, and we have seen hints of it. Maybe the closest example I can think of is the original iOS. One of our Partners, Felipe, says it’s the best digital design that has been made, and he might be right. It was simple, and everyone on earth from age two to ninety-nine knew how to use it, and it did some very complicated things. Maybe something like that has an ethos. But, short of that… no… I don’t think we’re there yet. Maybe the Google home page? I don’t know… it’s all still black &amp;amp; white TV. We’re not anywhere near Vignelli, Saville, or Rams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ve noticed that you refer to design as a discipline. What does that mean for you? Is it methodology? A mindset? What is it that makes how you view design a discipline?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is a hard thing to talk about. Most of design is very boring and laborious and terrifying. It’s mostly sitting at a desk or in a room and not knowing what to do. And that not knowing is scary and uncomfortable, and you spend half your time in that mindset, then the other half very meticulously and laboriously executing the idea to solve the problem. It’s “fear fear fear, a-ha!, dull dull dull” – that’s design. Because of that it’s tough to talk about - so I use words like discipline or medium to be able to talk about this really long sort of amorphous thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its best, design is problem solving with intent. I can think of design as a discipline - as something to be studied and revered in order to make better decisions or execute those decisions better. I can also think of it as a medium - an approach I believe in to problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think design is a process. I don’t think there is a pattern for good ideas. Having a good idea is not replicable. I don’t think that sticky-notes and whiteboarding will necessarily lead to a good idea. Maybe sometimes it does, but the truth is nobody knows where the next good idea is. And that’s scary. So we have to trick ourselves into not being scared, and try to think of design as something that you can study and get better at. And, you do. You get better over time, but it’s hard. It’s not any less scary, but it gets easier to express your ideas, and your ideas get better. I often think about a saying used in road cycling, “it never stops hurting,  you just get faster.” I think that’s what design is like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaking of inspiration and discipline, I’ve found that it is integral to find inspiration outside of one’s profession in order to stay engaged, focused, sane. The same with discipline. What are these for you? I gather you’re a road cyclist (same here). How does the personal Joe nurture the professional Joe?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to get stuck, or tired, or burnt out on design – especially if you stay on one project for a long time. I’ve spent years on the same project, and after a while you can’t tell what a good idea is anymore. Looking outside of design to reset is something everyone does. Some people do it with more intent than others, and I don’t know that I specifically do other activities in order to improve my design, but I think it probably happens accidentally. We all have those moments of surprising problem solving when we don’t expect it… in the middle of the night, or in the shower. It feels like the tip of the pencil gets dull, and you have to stop in order to sharpen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you mentioned, cycling is a hobby of mine and I’ve really grown to love it over the years. Like design, it’s not something you have to stop as you get older. You can be with it for decades, and I really like that. I love the aesthetic of cycling, the romance of a big race like the Tour de France, and the bikes themselves are incredibly beautiful to me. I think half of my love for cycling is drooling over the bikes. I love being alone on the road. It’s a great sense of quiet, that is sometimes interrupted by these sharp points of danger, which is a great way to snap yourself out of almost anything. I love that you can see a place very differently on a bike than you can in any other way: you get the details of walking somewhere slow, but you get the larger context of the surrounding space. I really learned New York on a bike, and I think it’s the best way to experience that city. It’s an amazing way to stop thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also, more recently, gotten into chess. I’m a terrible player, but I still enjoy playing. Trying to learn chess is a great way to feel bad about yourself – you constantly feel stupid – it’s extremely humbling. After some time, you start to be able to see how big the game really is, and it’s scary. It’s a terrifyingly complicated game that basically 5 people in the world are any good at. The rest of us are terrible, but that is actually sort of fun and comforting once you accept it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principles of chess also translate across other parts of life. A big part of it is the process of how to make a decision. You have to take your time and try to make the best choice, which is not necessarily the most obvious. This applies very well to design, of course. I have become better at taking the time to analyze the situation. I think chess taught me that. And it comes up about 100 times a day, so slowing down to try to make the best decision with intent is an incredibly useful habit. It’s also super fun, surprisingly social, and very addictive. It’s also the best game for iPhone, so you can always play someone wherever you are: it’s magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You mentioned in a recent exchange that part of what you wanted to change with starting Work &amp;amp; Co is the amount of time you spend actually designing — doing the thing we were trained to do: think and design. Do you at all feel like we’re moving away from these activities — thinking critically, engaging in discourse, drawing, designing with intent? In other words, do you feel we’re moving forward?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really love designing. It’s fun. And for whatever reason, I had to start a company in order to be able to get back to doing it. I’ve had the chance to do a lot of introspection about what I want to get out of my career — and out of design in general. There were times in my life that being good was the goal, or being well known, or doing something that is remembered, or leaving a legacy, or changing the world or something. After years of thought, I think I have settled on what is important to me, as far as work goes. I want to enjoy what I’m doing. That’s it. On a daily basis, every day, I want to go into the office and enjoy what I’m doing. I enjoy designing. I enjoy working through ideas. I enjoy working with other designers, developers, and strategists. I don’t enjoy spreadsheets, PowerPoint, staff resourcing, or thinking about profit margins. Seems simple enough, but to set up an environment where you can actually do this is pretty tricky. So, when thinking about starting a new company, this was my goal. That’s it. So far it’s working. And, there are all sorts of side effects that I didn’t really plan on. 1) My work is the best it’s ever been. 2) I’m the happiest I’ve ever been. 3) The company is successful. None of this was a primary goal, but while focusing on my simple goal, enjoying what I’m working on, everything else fell into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really just want to design. The act itself is the joy. That is the big revelation. The designing itself is the goal. It’s not any more complicated than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I referenced a growing artificial patina earlier — in part a jab at the pervasive nature of startup culture. What’s your take on what the startup landscape has done to design culture as a whole?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy, I’m divided on this one. Start-up culture is pretty divisive right now, and design gets mixed into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nice that so many startups value design and consider it a key tenant to their company’s success. Younger people, who are a big part of start-up culture, I think naturally value design more than previous generations – which I really appreciate. They’ve grown up in the world where Apple is king and design counts. So, you’ve got all these next generation Steve Jobs’ out there looking for their Jony Ive. I love that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dark side of that is when design becomes a buzz-word to promote another agenda. Right now, it feels like the vast majority of startups are only looking to make quick cash, and I hate seeing people promote “design” as a formulaic lever to do that. Design is sacred to me, and it’s hard to see startups abuse it and treat it like a commodity in order to reach their true goals. There is nothing worse to me than a salesman pretending to care about design because they think they can make more money that way. Charlatans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But. Anyway –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the net is actually positive. There is a whole community that didn’t really exist before that thinks design matters, and that is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My relationship with design can, at times, be quite tempestuous. There’s been times I wanted to just walk away. What is it that keeps you coming back day after day and working to get better? Has there ever been a time when you’ve thought “fuck it, I’m done”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh man, yes, for sure.  It’s hard to stay in it. It’s tiring. It’s taxing, and it never gets easier. Design is always hard and always scary. That will never go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a full time professional digital designer since I was 19. I’m 38 as of this interview. In the last almost 20 years I’ve had a lot of dark moments with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing that has always kept me going is the moment when the project you are working on is the best thing you have ever done. When you’re designing something, and you know it’s the best thing you’ve ever made… man… I like that feeling. I think I’m still getting to work on things that are better than anything I’ve ever made, so, I want to see where that goes. As I keep at it, keep sharpening that knife, it gets sharper and sharper and the design gets better and better. I’m working on a few things that are really pushing the craft. To me, that says ‘keep going, don’t stop now.’ It’s why I choose to stay so close to the work – that feeling of making good products is such a huge motivator to me sticking in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, working with other designers I look up to is a big one. This comes from my partners, my clients, and also younger designers at Work &amp;amp; Co. It’s so inspiring to see a young designer create a really thoughtful prototype and to work with them on promoting their craft. It makes me want to push harder on my own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any books that you would say have been influential in shaping your career? Ones you consistently come back to for inspiration?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could’ve just talked about this! I have a pretty decent collection of design books at home and in the office. I am always on the lookout for new ones. One of the nice things about living in Portland is that there is an amazing book store a few blocks from the office called Powell’s. I sneak over there on my lunch break pretty often to go look for books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what I look for is retrospectives of a designer or a company. I am not as into collections of a lot of people’s work; I really like buying books about a single entity. You can get inspired by the work itself, but also by their career. I’ve been designing for almost 20 years, and I get tired. It’s great to be able to look to people who did it for 50 and see how good they got. It makes me say “oh fuck, look at this designer – she’s 70 and still killing it – I want to be like her.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let’s see – here are a few books I have been into lately.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.creativereview.co.uk/cr-blog/2015/october/bob-noorda-design-celebrates-the-work-of-a-dutch-master-in-italy/&quot;&gt;Bob Noorda book&lt;/a&gt;, which I think is just titled Design is fantastic. Noorda was a designer at Unimark – maybe most famously he worked on the NY subway system with Vignelli – it’s amazing to see his work. Always so strong and bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1972municholympics.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Otl Aicher&lt;/a&gt; retrospective which is gorgeous. I only knew him from his 1972 Munich Olympic work, and it was eye opening to see his commercial design. I didn’t know he did the Lufthansa mark which is one of my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the Erik Spiekerman book &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1R7Zd7i&quot;&gt;Hello, I am Erik&lt;/a&gt; – it’s just nice to see a designer who is still working and killing it talk about design. Same goes for How To by Michael Beirut. Both of these books are fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I really like to read about design companies. I try to study the successes and failures of design companies in order to try to make good decisions with Work &amp;amp; Co. There is a book about Unimark called, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/24RKA2f&quot;&gt;Unimark International: The Design of Business and the Business Design&lt;/a&gt;, which is great. It’s the story of a superstar design company growing too big too fast and taking on too many things and exploding. Lots of great stories and lessons there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pentagram has about 500 books, and I try to read most of them. I look to them as a role model for creating something over a long period of time that consistently produces incredible work. In a few decades, I’d love to be on that level with our company for digital product design. So I’m trying to soak up as much as I can about them, which is helpful and inspiring. I also love following their new partners – I am really into the work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behance.net/njenworks&quot;&gt;Natasha Jen&lt;/a&gt; right now – she’s so daring, it scares me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lightning round - a few books I really like and recommend:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1LSaDzS&quot;&gt;Naoto Fukasawa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — Japanese industrial designer – most notably for Muji. I love the way he explains his thinking. He also co-authored a book just called Muji which is also great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1LSaEnE&quot;&gt;Vignelli from A-Z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — I read all the Vignelli books, but I like this one the most. It shows his good stuff, but also a lot of his goofy stuff (like the clothes… oof) – again it’s great to just hear him explain how he and Lella think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1LdwbXE&quot;&gt;40 Days of Dating&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — I think Jessica Walsh is incredible, and I try to stay up to date on everything she does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1Ldwd1O&quot;&gt;Helvetica / Objectified / Urbanized: The Complete Interviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — This book is the full transcripts of the interviews for the films – I love reading the longer form Interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1LSaJYt&quot;&gt;Swiss Graphic Design: The Origins and Growth of an International Style&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; — This is the book that I recommend for people when they are getting started, or people who don’t study design as part of their job. When developers or strategists ask for a book recommendation I always go with this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I think we all have something — something small — that we look forward to each day. Something that helps set the tone for the day or view it through a softened lense. For me, it’s that first cup of coffee after meditation each morning. What is it for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually wake up around 5AM and go to the gym – it sucks to get up, but it puts my head on straight. I have more patience, concentration, and stamina when I work out. It’s good for the body, but it’s great for the brain. If you want to have a good day at the office, have a good day at the gym first. I’m skinny and weak and I’m sure I look silly trying to bench press, but, just going makes me feel 100x better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you, I’m also into meditation. I use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.headspace.com/&quot;&gt;Headspace&lt;/a&gt; app, which is fantastic. I recommend it to anyone. It makes something pretty difficult to learn and maintain very simple. The UI is great, but the program itself is fantastic. It’s really an A+ product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love to read a bit right when I get to the office. Just reading for 10 minutes or so before I settle in gets my mind straight. I try to do it first thing. It sets to tone for the day. It’s nice to read just to calm yourself, but also, if you’re reading about great work it lets you see the big picture and not sweat the small problems so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve already built a solid foundation for Work &amp;amp; Co. What’s next? Where do you and your team want to take it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultimate goal is to be the first great digital design firm. Since the medium is so new, there really isn’t one yet. So – I think the best ad agency is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wk.com/&quot;&gt;W+K&lt;/a&gt;. I think the best branding agency is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolffolins.com/&quot;&gt;Wolf Ollins&lt;/a&gt;. I think the best graphic design agency is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pentagram.com/&quot;&gt;Pentagram&lt;/a&gt;. Best digital company? There isn’t one yet. We want to be that. As with the others, it will take time to get there. The plan is to take it slow, make long-term decisions, and focus. Focus on the work, on the people we work with, on making sure people have a good life, on recruiting the best people in the world, on making amazing products with our clients… repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it’s super simple – we want to keep getting better at what we’re already doing. Keep sharpening the pencil. Keep improving, learning new skills, improving our design theory, just keep going. And as we keep going, we want to make sure we’re enjoying every moment of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, simply to design is the goal, the reward is in the act itself. My next step? Just keep designing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Discourse, Rob Giampietro</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/01/rob-giampietro/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/01/rob-giampietro</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This interview was originally published on the now defunct oneskinnyj.com&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-sample_footnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-sample_footnote&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; site. I’m proud of this interview and am grateful to Rob for being so generous with his time and answers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hi Rob. Can you give our viewers a bit of history about yourself (where you went to school, where you’ve worked, and where you are now)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Minneapolis listening to a lot of jazz on ECM and going to the Walker Art Center whenever I could. Minneapolis, ECM, and the Walker’s design department and bookstore were all huge influences on me. I got a B.A. in Art from Yale and went to work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/medalists-william-drenttel-and-jessica-helfand/&quot;&gt;Winterhouse&lt;/a&gt;. Bill Drenttel and Jessica Helfand were very giving and had unique practice that allowed me space to develop as a designer — it was like a kind of grad school for me. When I left to go to New York I worked at the New York Times Magazine for almost a year — a great introduction to New York — before I joined Michael Bierut’s team at Pentagram as a freelancer, which was also an amazing learning experience. When my Winterhouse colleague Kevin Smith arrived in New York we began freelancing together and launched the studio Giampietro+Smith, which we ran for five years. I joined &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.projectprojects.com/&quot;&gt;Project Projects&lt;/a&gt; as a principal in 2010. Also in the mix I did a lot of design writing, was vice president of AIGA/NY, did a lot of teaching at Parsons, RISD, and SVA, and started a website of design writing and resources called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linedandunlined.com/&quot;&gt;Lined &amp;amp; Unlined&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve had quite a distinguished career, working at places like Winterhouse, Pentagram and now Project Projects. Were those positions ones that you actively sought after, or did any of them more or less fall into place naturally—one leading to the next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thankful for the opportunities I’ve had. Any career is a mix of skill, luck, and persistence, and I’ve relied on all three. A few ideas have served as helpful guides: 1) actively engage people and places that are interesting to me, 2) cultivate and expand my interests not just as a designer but as a person in the world, and 3) be open to whatever opportunities presented themselves without predetermining their outcomes too much. When I first moved to the city, I showed my portfolio to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pentagram.com/partners/#/15/&quot;&gt;Abbott Miller&lt;/a&gt;, whose work I’d long admired. I was hoping for a job working for him, but he surprised me by saying, “Have you ever thought about teaching? You’d be great.” He introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tdc.org/officers/charles-nix/&quot;&gt;Charles Nix&lt;/a&gt; at Parsons and I taught there for the next 8 years. I was 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why graphic design? I mean, why not something else? What opportunities does graphic design provide that you feel so compelled to engage in this profession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design’s such a pliable profession — there’s a tremendous amount you can do under the umbrella of design, and that was always enticing to me. I love the idea of making things that reach many people. I love the social aspect of being a designer: meeting many different kinds of people, engaging my curiosities and passions. I love language and I am a deeply systematic and analytical person in both my design and my writing. And I have a longstanding fascination with typography — it seems to sit in the valley between language and form, and I like to hang out there too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On your blog, Lined &amp;amp; Unlined, you write quite critically on a range of interests—design, film, poetry, pedagogy. How does writing influence your design practice? Is it an essential part of the process?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing plays many roles. It lets me reflect on practice much the same way teaching does, and it also lets me advocate for ideas, work, and people I think are important and innovative within the profession. At the same time it creates a space outside daily practice — writing for me often happens at night and on weekends — to develop and explore ideas. Often the best way to find out what I think about something is to write about it. There’s this assumption that you must know about something to write about it, but often the process of writing about something mirrors the process of learning about it. Certain pieces I write I know will be key pieces, but other shorter writing is almost like a gym workout — it keeps my mind sharp and my eyes open. I’m not sure that writing’s essential for me. Sometimes it’s addictive and sometimes it’s exhausting. It’s almost always rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you become involved with David Reinfurt, Stuart Bailey, and Dot Dot Dot?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Elliman, whose writing and typographic work I admired before I arrived at Yale, is probably the common link. David was a the T.A. for a class I took with Paul, and it was also during that semester that Stuart came to town and Paul suggested we meet for coffee. We all stayed in touch. I mailed away for the first &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dot-dot-dot.us/&quot;&gt;Dot Dot Dot&lt;/a&gt; and it came with a kind note from Stuart inviting me to contribute to a future issue. They’re my favorite people to write for, everything I’ve done with them is something I’m proud of. They create a very special environment for ideas to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For many designers—and I’d imagine for many other professionals—the act of writing is approached with caution, even fear. Can you talk a little bit about your process for writing (how you approach it)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like anything, you get better at it the more you do it. This is why the blog and doing shorter written pieces is important. Every piece I’ve done has developed a little differently, but just like design it works best for me when there’s a collaboration — in this case, between myself and the editor of the piece. This is why David and Stuart are so important in the writing I’ve done for Dot Dot Dot. We discuss different approaches, references, send things back-and-forth over a few weeks or even months. Then at a certain point it’s time to start writing. Often I have a lot of fragments, sentences or phrasings I like. I also try to have a pool of quotes or quick section outlines floating around in different text windows. The writing almost starts to get “laid out” like a piece of design in this way. I think confidence also builds the more you write, which helps with the fear you have when you start a new piece. I place a huge amount of trust in my ear, the way the language sounds. I’ve rewritten pieces that were fine language-wise but didn’t sound good to my ear — that’s the poet in me I guess. I wrote a Dot Dot Dot piece about the 100th Chapter of Robert Musil’s book &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1MjG19R&quot;&gt;The Man Without Qualities&lt;/a&gt;, and I knew I wanted the piece to end with the biographical image of Musil getting kicked out of the library for smoking, a habit which lead to his early death and left the novel unfinished. I must have rewritten the last paragraph 60 times before I finally got it to sound right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do words and language influence your design work? At any point does semiotic theory become part of the framework for developing a concept? Further, if semiotic theory does play a role, do you find yourself subscribing to any particular tradition—Saussurean or Peircean?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words influence me a great deal, though I don’t think about language in terms of semiotics all that often. I’m very familiar with Saussure and studied him as part of my introduction to literary theory; less so with Pierce but I was just reading up on him now and enjoyed the brief introduction I found — I’m fascinated by the different attributes and aspects of language, especially paradoxes, and in the thinking they reveal. I love some of language’s more formal and sensory qualities. I love the look of language, especially in conceptual art (artists like Lawrence Weiner, Ed Ruscha, John Baldessari, Richard Kostelanetz, Kay Rosen), concrete poetry (poets like Emmett Williams, Dieter Rot, and Eugen Gomringer), along with almost all of Oulipo. I also love the sound of language in more mainstream poetry (poets like Robert Frost, Wallace Stevens, Elizabeth Bishop, Frank O’Hara, and Nicholas Christopher) and contemporary literature (writers like Lydia Davis, Geoff Dyer, Nicholson Baker, and David Means). I like the exploration of genres, modes, reflexivity, and the written text as something that is constructed and allowed to reveal its own construction in order to produce meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying on the same topic of influence, does what you have experienced as a professional practitioner come through in your approach to pedagogy? Are their certain elements to the practice—things that might not be getting addressed in academia—that you believe should have a stronger presence in design education today?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s much like the writing — my practice as a designer feeds my practice as a teacher, and my practice as a teacher in turn gives me ideas and ways of communicating my practice as a designer. They reinforce one another. In terms of where education’s headed, I’ve just finished a long essay that covers design education over the last decade or more, and I think we’re seeing an increased amount of merging between the academic and professional space. In the early ‘90s the design academy was seen as a space that was alternative to practice and its interest was largely theoretical and formally engaged, and there are some for whom it still functions that way. But I think designers increasingly consider school to be part of the production their own professional lives, and they consider learning to be an ongoing and integral process to the development of work and one’s development as a designer. And as a result of this “embeddeness” of the culture of school in everyday design practice, you have more situations where designers are setting up places to learn and exchange ideas — whether it’s conferences, participatory exhibitions, websites, etc. Our own interconnectedness via technology only accelerates and encourages this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;e are living in an increasingly techno-visual culture—where combinations of complex technologies and new visual lexicons are born almost constantly. What is the role of [graphic] design in this new culture and how has the field changed over the last several years? What do you feel has been the most significant shift in the design world within the last five years?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is a reflexive mechanism in culture — it both helps to both set new cultural agendas and reinforce existing ones. The same shifts that have been happening outside the design world for the last five years are helping to shape the most interesting things happening inside design. The more responsive and contextual design can be, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We seem to be in the midst of a shift—a large body of designers moving away from the “client services” aspect of design, and instead pursuing more entrepreneurial endeavors. Do you feel that this is a result of the designer realizing more can be done with that skill, that design can do more than just sell products—it can sell ideologies and philosophy? Or is this shift in behavior a reaction to something larger?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve always seen designers seek opportunities and models for practice outside of commissioned work — whether it was setting up publishing programs, advocating for cultural resistance, building institutions that centralize and reinforce design’s cultural capital, or finding solace in a world of “self-initiated” projects. In many ways, each of these alternative practice models is a product of their times, and the shift to entrepreneurial endeavors you mention is no different. I think we should, as designers, keep inventing more of these as time goes on. But I think as long as design’s central narrative is one of a problem-solving, analytical discipline, then the need and opportunity for service-driven practice will persist and endure. What’s notable, if anything, is the degree to which a ‘90s-era world of self-initiated work has broadened, in the ‘00s, and with the help of the internet, to a world far beyond the self — it’s now a whole design culture, large enough to support the careers of certain designers without the need for them to frame their practices through service. But I’ll sound a cautionary note here: while I think it’s good to launch projects that other designers think are great, I think it’s much more essential that designers look beyond the design sphere in framing new opportunities for themselves. These are the projects — self-initiated, entrepreneurial, commissioned, bartered, speculative, or otherwise — that I look forward to most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s switch gears and round this out with some Project Projects talk: the studio has an enviable portfolio of clients in the arts and architecture sectors and the work always seems to pulse with intellect. Why focus on those sectors? What design opportunities present themselves in these genres that might not in other sectors—like retail or hospitality?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I think there was an appeal in the idea that the arts and architecture represented a intriguingly distinct area of culture from the overtly commercial. While both sectors have clearly commercial aspects and implications, there’s also something intangibly noncommercial about them, something belonging to the world of ideas alone. This created an early set of affinities, both to institutions and to people, which developed into a ready source of projects. As time has passed I think we’ve discovered new and different reasons for our ongoing interest in these sectors. Both art and architecture are “founding disciplines” of graphic design, for example, and as a result share many of the same critical discussions and historical references. And both, as visual and spatial disciplines, have a wealth of aesthetically-motivated individuals who encourage design work that is ambitious and perhaps a bit outside the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top five books a designer must read that have nothing to do with design?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These have both nothing and everything to do with design, which is why designers might enjoy them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark McGurl’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1MjCEji&quot;&gt;The Program Era&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;J.L. Austin’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1FEEaEL&quot;&gt;How to Do Things with Words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Gleick’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1MjCMPN&quot;&gt;The Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lucien Dallenbach’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1FEEfsa&quot;&gt;The Mirror in the Text&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marcel Benabou’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1FEEh3f&quot;&gt;Why I Have Not Written Any of My Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For those designers who are walking down that path to starting their own studio: what advice would you like to impart to them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be fun to come up with 10 of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An untended garden quickly becomes a field: plant what you want to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have partners, but don’t do the same things: make sure you both do something you enjoy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire people for what they can teach you, not for what you can teach them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone should be able to take criticism: creative trust is built on critical honesty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design is only one part of the puzzle: savor the discussion, development, debate, and dissemination of your work just as much as the making of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goals may be arbitrary, but not having them will be maddening when there’s no one else to tell you if you’re doing a good job: set 3-month, 6-month, and 1-year goals at the outset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you take your favorite clients out to lunch, it’s a good time to propose what you’d like to do together next.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowing more designers doesn’t necessarily translate into having good clients: spend your development time wisely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be known for something: it helps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You will never work harder than when you’re building something: find balance. Sometimes the best way to solve a creative problem is to take a vacation or read a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-sample_footnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;oneskinnyj.com was a moniker and online repository I used for several years. It housed the aforementioned interview series, which I will be resurrecting here. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-sample_footnote&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Beyond Familiar</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/01/01/beyond-familiar/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/01/01/beyond-familiar</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.offscreenmag.com&quot;&gt;Offscreen Magaine&lt;/a&gt;, Issue &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.offscreenmag.com/issue3/&quot;&gt;No3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently visited &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chattanooga,_Tennessee&quot;&gt;Chattanooga&lt;/a&gt; in Tennessee. It’s my hometown and a trip there is never easy for me. There is always a point during my visits when I become emotional as slivers of my past — the good and the bad — resurface. There are parts of the city that conjure up memories that I’d rather not revisit: painful breakups, a car accident, and familial drama. But there are also locations that provide an overwhelming source of happiness and fondness — the hundreds of beautiful days I spent outside rock-climbing with friends, the amazing job I had at an outdoor shop during high-school and college, and my first kiss with Erin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While growing up here, the city always felt comfortable and safe. I knew the people and I knew my way around. Getting lost in this place was almost impossible. The city was predictable, and as I grew older and my curiosity stronger, it didn’t offer what I needed: unfamiliarity and opportunities for discovery. My hometown became destined to be just that: my hometown, a place where I grew up. So I did what I needed to do and moved away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my most recent visit home, while wandering through the town and past some of my usual spots, I began to realise not only how my feelings had changed, but how the city itself had changed. I was now an outside observer visiting a place that felt foreign, despite the familiarity. This was not the hometown I knew anymore. This was not that muted city with only one decent coffee shop and a notable population of vagabonds. This town felt alive and vibrant; its pulse youthful&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-gig_city&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-gig_city&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I found myself discovering things to love; things I hadn’t encountered before. These discoveries were nourishing and restoring my relationship with the place that I once couldn’t wait to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of us, there’s a period in our adolescence when we can’t wait to leave home. We yearn to strike out on our own, carve our own path, and prove that we belong in this world. We need to test ourselves, to prove that we can provide for ourselves and accomplish something. Leaving home is never easy. Change, in general, is never easy, but it’s necessary if we’re to allow ourselves the chance to grow. I’m reminded of a quote by Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr. who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A mind that is stretched by a new experience can never go back to its old dimensions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find a lot of parallels between the experiences I’ve had returning home and the relationship I have with our industry. I love what I do and find comfort in knowing that discoveries in technology will continue to push the boundaries of what we do and how we do it. I count myself lucky to be engaged in a creative pursuit that rewards curiosity. But I still get burnt out, run down, and frustrated. Our work not only demands innovative thinking with a pragmatic approach, but managing clients, project budgets, growing to-do lists, and the elusive inbox zero. Our field is evolving at an ever-increasing pace, and if we want to remain relevant we, too, must evolve right along with it. As a digital product designer, change is a responsibility I owe not only myself, but the audiences my work serves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, over the years I’ve learned that professional growth isn’t just about remaining abreast of the advances in our field. Keeping up with the changes in our profession is necessary, but in the process, it is all too easy to close ourselves off in an echo-chamber of design and technology. Sometimes we need to step away from our professional roles and pursue other interests in order to grow. Experiences we have outside the realm of our expertise can help us to provide additional layers of insight to the projects we take on. Our work may become better as a result and provide new perspectives to those who see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had always been interested in psychology, so several years ago I began pursuing a degree in behavioural psychology. I was presented with fascinating facts about the way we behave and the influencers of that behaviour. Entering an unknown territory and engaging with an entirely new subject matter helped me become a better user experience designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left home and gained a new perspective on why I loved where I was from. Stepping away and leaving the familiar behind, if only for a short period of time, can help us broaden our horizons. A renewed vision brings with it a restored focus. We can return to work with a deeper respect for what we do and who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-gig_city&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chattanooga has recently seen a resurgance of a growing wave ofentrepreneurialism, thanks in part to the presence of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thegigtank.com/&quot;&gt;gig-speed internet infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-gig_city&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
