<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Justin Kropp</title>
 <link href="http://justinkropp.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://justinkropp.com/"/>
 <updated>2016-02-09T20:11:48-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://justinkropp.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Justin Kropp</name>
   <email>justinkropp@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Dan Mall</title>
   <link href="http://justinkropp.com/2016/02/01/dan-mall/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://justinkropp.com/2016/02/01/dan-mall</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/image.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dan Mall&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This interview was originally published on the now defunct oneskinnyj.com site.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First of all, congrats on everything that has happened over this past year! It’s just incredible. Was the decision to go out on your own more difficult with the birth of your daughter Sidda?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Thanks! It was definitely difficult to venture out on my own so quickly after just having a daughter, but it was even more motivating. One of the biggest reasons for starting my own studio is the prospect of being at home more with my wife Emily and daughter Sidda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been one to shy away from big life changes all at once. Shortly after getting married, I left a great job at “Happy Cog”:http://happycog.com/ and a city I grew up in (Philadelphia) for another great job at “Big Spaceship”:http://bigspaceship.com/ in a city I’ve barely visited (Brooklyn). I’m really blessed to have a wife who’s always up for the newest adventure with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: Your new endeavor has a great statement: “envision and design wondrous places for human connection.” Can you talk a bit more about what it means to build a meaningful experience that makes one feel connected to another?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I think the most successful and authentic brands are ones that make real connections between themselves and their customers, and—even better—between customers themselves. A lot of brands think that good digital advertising is simply broadcasting their own messages through digital channels like Twitter and Facebook, but that’s a really old school mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As “SuperFriendly”:http://superfriend.ly/, I’m really interested in working with brands that are looking to make interesting connections. Digital affords a great opportunity for instantaneous connection, and it’s a shame when brands don’t take advantage of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, one of my favorite connections recently is “SPENT”:http://playspent.org/, a wonderful site created by friends “Nick Jones”:http://narrowdesign.com/, “Able Parris”:http://ableparris.com/, “Karla Mickens”:http://karlamickens.com/, and others at “McKinney”:http://mckinney.com/. The site allows you to role play as if you were homeless. It’s one of the most engaging experiences I’ve had online in a long time, and I think this kind of emotional connection is really few and far between online nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can do my part in the work that I do to help create these kinds of experiences, I’ll consider myself very fortunate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: From a design standpoint, what do you think makes that experience engaging? How does a designer approach addressing that powerful of a message? What do they have to consider?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: For me, engaging experiences are all about people and the powerful connections made between them. Cave painters, musicians, marketplace vendors, and countless historical professionals have know that for centuries; we’re getting good at figuring out what that means in pixels, but our medium is still so new that we still have a lot of room for exploration. As designers, it’s easy to get so caught up in the craft—choosing the right typeface, color scheme, markup—that we sometimes miss that small moments that create the whole experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: What experiences from Happy Cog and Big Spaceship will you reflect upon and use in your new endeavor? For instance, we all suffer from burnout from time to time. How did you handle burnout back then and how do you handle it now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A:  I’ve always strived for a 40-hour work week. Sometimes that’s not possible, but I try my darnedest to make it happen. I think it’s easy to believe that throwing more time at a problem will birth a solution, but I’ve found that some of the work I’m most proud of has come from the fact that there was no time available. For me, burnout happens when something in my life goes out of balance. If I’m working too much, then I’m doing something else too little, like spending time with family or rehearsing with my band. Avoiding burnout means maintaining the balance I’ve established and not allowing one thing to dominate my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: I have to agree that spending too much time on a project can definitely turn into a burden. I also believe that striving for perfection falls into that same camp, but coming to terms with imperfection in our design work is often easier said than done. What are your thoughts on chasing the perfect in our work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: It’s a small distinction, but I prefer to strive for perfection in order to achieve excellence. Maybe it comes from my Christian perspective, but the idea that we humans can create anything free of flaws is a difficult notion to stomach. I do believe that it’s important to do the best job that we can for our clients and for ourselves. I think that’s a worthy standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: You mention that rehearsing with your band helps to alleviate a bit of burnout. Is it simply the act of stepping away from your profession that helps, or is it engaging in another creative outlet? Perhaps both? Have you ever considered taking an extended hiatus from design?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Wow, interesting question. I’ve never seriously considered taking a sabbatical, both because I love what I do and it’s a way I can provide for my family. During a Q&amp;amp;A session at a conference, a student asked me what I do to overcome creative block. Completely unprepared for that question, I tried to answer honestly and was actually surprised as what I said. I said I don’t believe in creative block. Huh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll caveat that. Our industry (and related ones) often herald the powers of “the creatives” as divine inspiration waiting to be channelled, like we sit around waiting for a moment of eureka! Pfft. I don’t know about anyone else, but design is hard work for me. Creative block definitely happens, but it needs to be worked through. Take a break, get some water, read a book… then sit your butt back down at your desk and get to work! For me, conquering creative block is about encouraging and creating multiple failures to create success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: When taking on new clients - how do approach educating them about how a creative project unfolds? Demystify it in a manner of speaking. Do you find that clients like to know about the various phases of a project and what’s involved in each?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I prefer to think of client education in terms of collaboration. I don’t have a typical process. Sure, there are things I gravitate towards, but they’re more like weapons in my arsenal as opposed to steps I follow every time. For every new client at SuperFriendly, part of our first conversation is to tell them that we don’t have a process that we make every client go through. We have a framework, a list of possibilities for what we might do, but we really love working directly with our clients to figure out the best process for that particular team. On some projects, wireframes are exactly what’s needed; on others, we shun them completely. Some projects start with visual design; others start by diving right into HTML prototypes. I think it’s unfair to blindly try and mold clients into a process. I’d much rather create the right circumstances to make my team and theirs more successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: I’m always fascinated about the stories behind starting one’s own business or leaving a job to start a studio. Do you mind talking about what led up to you taking the plunge? Had you been considering the move for a while or did a series of events present themselves that just made the decision easy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: My daughter was really the motivation for going out on my own. I remember leaving the house one day for work when Sidda was about 2 or 3 months old. When I got home that night, she looked directly at me, a skill (focusing and following one specific thing) she had seemingly developed that day. I asked my wife when she had learned that, but, being a stay-at-home mom, it was something she had noticed for a while already. I realized I was missing things about my daughter’s life, and I didn’t want that to happen anymore. I started to look for ways that I could work from home so I could be around for Sidda as she grew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting home for the holidays, we mentioned to my parents that we were thinking about moving back to Philadelphia to be closer to family. My dad mentioned that he still owned some property from a personal care home he and my mom ran before my grandparents passed away. He offered us the property, an old 3000 sq. ft church-turned-house. It was more than enough space for us to live and even had some potential for me to create some studio space if I needed it. The idea for SuperFriendly was born that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: For those considering venturing out on there own, what are the top five things they should do first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Everyone’s different so what works for one might not work for others, but here are a few things that worked for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototype your business. As designers and developers, we love to prototype; it’s in our nature and our work is made better for it. But it baffles me when we don’t take that approach to other aspects. I knew that I’d someday run my own business. For one year, I prototyped that business: I worked a full time job, came home to eat dinner, then worked another full-time job moonlighting. It was a decision that Emily and I made together, knowing that the sacrifices would be worth the effort. Knowing that I had a full-time salary to rely on gave me tremendous liberty to experiment with how I would bill and charge, the way I liked to work, and what things would make me most successful. When the opportunity presented itself to finally start that business, I was ready. Day one to the world was actually year one.
Hire people that whose talents offset your weaknesses. My project manager, CPA firm, and lawyer help me take care of things I don’t do well but have been crucial for me to run a successful business.
Decide whether you’re a freelancer or a design business owner. Both have their pros and cons. Freelancers have the advantage of being scrappy but give off the connotation of always burning the midnight oil and having discounted prices. Being a design business owner can be more lucrative and earn you bigger projects, but it often means more administrative tasks and being more strict about your business operations.
Fail on someone else’s dime. If you’re a student or new to the design field, I highly recommend getting some experience working for an established studio before venturing out on your own. Gain a wide variety of experiences for how business runs. See what things you like about how others start run their businesses, and be critical about the things you would change if you ran your own. It’s much less costly to learn from others’ mistakes and victories.
Do work you enjoy. While I’ve always maintained a hybrid skillset of both designing and coding, I found very quickly that there’s a point where coding sucks the life out of me. By recognizing that and hiring people that are good/enjoy it instead of trudging through myself, I find that I have more satisfaction in my work, and I can really focus on attract work that I love to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: Each new year brings with it new opportunities. Many look at the start of the new year as a chance to shed old skin, start new habits, and outline overly-ambitious goals. What are you most looking forward to in 2013 and what do you want to accomplish in the next 12 months?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Lots! I’ve got a whole range of things to accomplish this year, both professional and personal (I’ll likely turn it into a blog post eventually). It ranges from finding more time for myself and my family, eliminating student loans, getting an better bed, traveling more, building a product that’s been on my mind for the last few years, more date nights with my wife, planning a conference, learning to swim, and lots more!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Where’s the Finish Line?</title>
   <link href="http://justinkropp.com/2016/01/08/finish-line/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://justinkropp.com/2016/01/08/finish-line</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was originally published with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/wheres-the-finish-line-examining-success-in-design/&quot;&gt;AIGA&lt;/a&gt; in 2009.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paris Hilton is a superstar. This celebrity icon is best known for her role on The Simple Life television series and the scandalous sex tape that made its way around the internet. Her rise to stardom has taken the route followed by many famous socialites—her fame and success are accidental and inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a year younger than Hilton, Natalie Portman, 28, is an actor who has achieved both celebrity status and professional success. Portman has been a prominent actor since her childhood. She took a brief break from performing to complete her degree in psychology from Harvard in 2003, and then pursued graduate coursework. She is both an artist and a scholar and has worked to produce quality work in both roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most professions have their own versions of success. These include, in some form, wealth, recognition, awards, speaking engagements, publishing deals and more. Our culture has grown accustomed to these models and expects nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving our admiration is the desire to author our own success, especially if it can parallel the stardom we are so used to seeing and reading about in tabloids—online and off. In mainstream culture, celebrity and success are far from synonymous. Celebrity can be attained for arbitrary reasons, as we have witnessed with Paris Hilton—fame does not necessarily stem from professional achievement or even personal satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In graphic design, however, this is not the case. Design’s celebrities have earned notoriety as a result of their success—for their body of work in the service of clients. Their stardom reflects the quality of work they produce as well as their ambition to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our celebrities, like most, are easy to recognize—at least within the confines of the graphic design community. They appear often in the industry’s standard publications being lauded for this project or that. They are the keynote speakers at major conferences and events. They are the subjects of documentaries and books. We hold their work up to high standards and we are quick to criticize them when those standards are not met. These design idols are the leaders of our profession, setting trends and providing the critical discourse that becomes the backbone of much of what we do and what we think about. And like the demographic of the audiences they inspire and influence, these designers run the full range of ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last observation is reassuring. The community of graphic designers is getting bigger, with a larger number of young practitioners whose skills surpass their experience. As business schools begin to understand the importance of design and adopt our model of “design thinking,” we will be facing a more competitive and specialized collective than ever before. We face more pressure to achieve and succeed at an earlier stage of our lives. Like most mainstream celebrities, who risk being considered “washed up” when entering their 40s, young designers feel like failures if they don’t get early public recognition. Thinking like this is a sure way to end up burned out and disillusioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malcolm Gladwell’s recent bestseller Outliers explores how people manage to achieve greatness in various fields of endeavor. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/video-gain-2008-gladwell&quot;&gt;Gladwell’s research reveals&lt;/a&gt; that “genius” doesn’t only come to brilliant young prodigies (like Picasso), but is also attained by people who plod along for decades (like Cezanne). Today’s youth-obsessed culture tends to focus on young upstarts and new talent, but designers achieve success across ages and generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Reinfurt is a critical thinker and maker. Those who don’t know his name might have read his ideas while thumbing the pages of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dot-dot-dot.us/&quot;&gt;Dot Dot Dot&lt;/a&gt;—an underground magazine published by his workshop and bookstore Dexter Sinister, which Reinfut runs with Stuart Bailey. Reinfurt has managed to blur the lines between the standard client-based studio practice with that of critical research and investigation into all areas of our field: print, web, interactive, video, installation and even performance. His work has transcended the sphere of mainstream graphic design to receive recognition by the international art world—and all this while in his mid-30s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to Reinfurt’s quick start, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/medalist-edfella&quot;&gt;Ed Fella&lt;/a&gt;’s career took years to germinate. The artist, educator, and graphic designer hails from Detroit, where he spent 30 years working in the advertising business before attending graduate school at Cranbrook. Fella received his MFA in 1987 at age 49 and has gone on to have a long and influential career while teaching at the California Institute of the Arts. In design culture he is widely known and revered for his playful typographic compositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/medalist-paulascher&quot;&gt;Paula Scher&lt;/a&gt; entered the profession in the early 1970s, a time when when women faced the glass ceiling in nearly every corporate structure. She started at CBS records, moved to Epic, and then back at CBS as an art director. Her quick wit and thick skin served her well in the company of men. For Scher, design has always been about making. It has been about producing work and being challenged by that work. Considered one of the world’s most influential graphic designers, she has achieved a success and celebrity status that most of us dream about, and she has been able to do so over a long period of time while satisfying her internal desire to produce work that is unconventional, emotional, political, dimensional and poetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marian Bantjes calls herself a “graphic artist,” and it is under this designation that she has gained an international reputation for ornamental type and organic lettering that brims with originality and brilliance. Prior to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/singing-the-blues&quot;&gt;becoming the Bantjes&lt;/a&gt; we are all familiar with, she was, much like Fella, a working designer at a traditional agency in Vancouver, BC, Canada. In 2003 she left her conventional career behind and started a journey of redefinition—a journey that has lead her to immense accomplishment. When she redefined herself she was 40 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/young-and-restless-an-interview-with-dress-code&quot;&gt;G. Dan Covert and Andre Andreev&lt;/a&gt; tells a different tale. Now 28 and 24, respectively, they operate the small studio, dress code, in New York City and have found themselves in the spotlight since the release of their book Never Sleep: Graduating to Graphic Design, published in April 2009. Energetic, exuberant, and loaded with everything from student projects to personal IM communications, Never Sleep is not a disciplined retrospective so much as the collective musings of two young guys who can’t believe how fast they got ahead after graduating. Dan and Andre are the new guys on the block and already enjoying success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These designers represent the immense talent that can be found throughout our industry and at every point in the timeline—from rookies to veterans. While the aforementioned group may be touted as successes and celebrities, their achievements have been both internal and authored. Their models of success derived from not how much money they were going to make or who was going to give them the credit they deserved, but rather from how they were going to continue to produce work they believe in. Without this inherent belief in our work, our successes will be fleeting and disappointing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Naz Hamid</title>
   <link href="http://justinkropp.com/2015/10/31/naz-hamid/"/>
   <updated>2015-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://justinkropp.com/2015/10/31/naz-hamid</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/naz-hamid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Naz Hamid&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This interview was originally published on the now defunct oneskinnyj.com site. Naz was an early interview on the site and I really enjoyed getting to know him more through our exchange. Above photo by &lt;a href=&quot;http://williamcouch.com/&quot;&gt;William Couch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I think it is safe to say that almost every designer, at some point, considers opening their own studio or practice. For some, that realization comes early. When did you decide it was time to do your own thing? What was the first thing you did after making the decision to form Weightshift?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two forms of &lt;a href=&quot;http://weightshift.com&quot;&gt;Weightshift&lt;/a&gt; — when it was just me and the moniker I operated under, and then what it is today, with four core people and regular people we work with. I’ll answer the question more so to the latter phase of the studio. Moving West to San Francisco had an impact in that I was searching for the next thing — whether to work for one of the companies that I’ve been fortunate to have been offered work at or just keeping doing what I do, but bigger. It was the second part I chose. I place a huge importance on quality of life and independence and so it made sense. The first thing I did when I made the decision to make Weightshift a studio comprised of more than just myself, was to actually register the studio as a company with the state of California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you already have current clients in place or did you have to seek out new work to make the decision feasible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had existing clients but again, it was a re-invention of the studio. Now it was many, and so, the work and clients, had to scale. A key client, who we’re fortunate to now call friends and collaborators, was  the first client we had as a group and that set things in motion. We’ve been fortunate enough that word of mouth, referrals and the website along with articles we’ve written and other community-driven exposure has led clients to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When the time came to actually attract new clients, how did you go about doing so? Email? Cold calls? Networking opportunities (events)? Did anything seem to work more effectively than another?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been very, very, very fortunate prior to the group studio and now, as a group, that we’ve not had to email or cold call or network to get the studio name out there. Certainly, I think doing those things might bring in more business, but we’ve seemed to figure out who our clients are and who we want to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s important to the studio culture and general happiness. Once you identify the types of people you enjoy working with and the kind of work and clients you want to work with, you figure out how to put your best foot forward in getting that kind of work. Your ideals, principles and approach, if you put them out correctly, will hopefully resonate with the right people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, what works is doing good work for the kinds of people we want to attract but also giving back to the community that we’re a part of everyday. Whether that means writing articles, or sharing knowledge, releasing free code or making web applications open to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many studios strike a balance between accepting projects they really want to work on and working on projects that are solely to pay the bills. Were you selective about the type of work you were accepting or did you find yourself in a position, early on, where you had to accept less glamorous work to pay the bills?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the answer is above, but yes, we try to be selective in the kinds of clients we work with. Because we’re a small studio, we can do that, as we tend to have a full load that works out to a quarterly timeline. We tend to get booked in 3-4 month chunks, but we’ve been taking on smaller, shorter and interesting projects in between the bigger ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the studio, I did indeed have to take on what work I could find. There’s a part of me that will never stop the hustle. When you pursue a path that’s independent, you have this hustling streak — this constant ebb and flow in how you’re sizing up work and how the work defines you. If you work hard and you do the kind of work that you feel closely aligns with what you like working on, you’ll get into a rhythm and find people to jam with that appreciate what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From your experiences thus far, what are some key factors into starting and maintaining a successful studio practice? Apart from the obvious, what do you feel best serves that newbie striking out on his or her own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is the biggest. I know some people like to call work “play”. But I think that blurs the line between personal time and professional time and some people can’t turn it off when they should. When you’re younger, it’s easy to burn the midnight oil. I did it throughout my early and late 20s — I was a true insomniac! But that’s how things got done and you can really be prolific that way. However, I think the landscape’s changed — you can work on just a few things and make those things be great and make it work just as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondarily and supplementary to the above is that you should develop a culture. Have morals, guidelines, criteria and an environment that supports the studio. Since it’s typically a client services driven venture, be sure to set up the studio and the people working within it, for success. Whatever that means to you. The beauty of studios, like people, are the different approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You were in Chicago for quite some time before heading out west. Why the move? How has that move affected Weightshift—if at all?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winters! Chicago has hardcore winters. Primarily, my wife and I got tired of the weather. We like moderate to tropical climates. Given my background, I’m surprised I lasted as long as I did in Chicago. It’s a great city, but for active people like ourselves, it became tough to deal with mentally and physically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move has been great for the studio. It really has. Since it coincided with the time I decided to make Weightshift a larger and shared venture, I’ve personally been amazed, humbled and thankful that it’s working out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a more direct manner, we’ve become start-up driven in a way. Most, if not all, of our current clients are start-ups, technology-oriented or creatively-aligned and being here seems to attract that even more so than before. Granted, the work begets the work. It’s a good thing though — we’ve been able to help and shape products, user experiences and brands while they’re small and growing and continue to help them as they mature and become successful. It’s a wonderful experience to be able to form and grow into relationships with these companies. It feels familial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you pursue self-initiated work to supplement down time or slow months? Do you feel that self initiated work can help develop a solid following—from either clients or peers? And further, when doing this work—such as Interhoods or SitBy.Us—how do you go about reaching out to the right people to get it done?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The studio is constantly thinking about internal ideas and as you’ve noted, we’ve produced some of these publicly. There’s a running list of tiny to ambitious ideas that we keep adding to, to see if any keep calling to us to make or develop. Sometimes, it’s about the right opportune moment or when a certain technology or service has matured or is offered to make the initial difficulty now far more realistic. It’s pretty amazing to think that an idea you may have that you shelve because of lack of resources becomes within grasp because someone else out there is offering it as a service or gratis. Our community is generally super-helpful and giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do feel that it does help — making things for the community does undoubtedly foster goodwill within peers and clients. Though I don’t think we’ve ever executed anything expressly with that purpose. We’re just not that calculated! We do it because we ourselves want to see it out there or because it’s just a cool little thing that could be useful to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does blogging fit into all this? Weightshift maintains a studio blog where you post about a range of topics—personal and professional. Is the blog—from a studio perspective—still a powerful tool for updating your audience and showing your engagement with your profession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love writing. I wish I were a hundred times better than I am. I wish the studio wrote more. We traded in quantity for quality though. And given how busy we’ve been, it’s been hard to put words to screen. We’re trying at the moment to write a little more frequently. I’m personally trying to get it into part of the discipline and culture but we also feel a deep commitment to our clients and customer service and so that usually wins out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogs are still great. I wish more of my favorite people wrote. But I understand why they don’t as well. A lot of the conversation has definitely moved to Twitter and it’s an extremely powerful tool in that respect. The brevity is still refreshing all these years later. I actually think it makes people better writers. I sometimes feel that I can say in 140 characters more than if I rattled away for 800 words. Clear and concise, no?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When starting to reach out to new clients and establishing a relationship, what do you feel is most important to maintain that relationship and present yourself in the best possible way? Is there a perfect balance between personal and professional connections with clients?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professionalism goes a long way. Being prepared. Staying classy. Patience is indeed a virtue. Communication is EVERYTHING. Respect limits. Respect working hours. It’s business, not personal. Be yourselves. Don’t over share. Be polite. Be respectful. LISTEN. Fight for what you believe. Fight for users. Fight for your clients. Be PRO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in all of that is the perfect storm of studio, client and audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What have been some of the most rewarding experiences while running your own business? What about some of the scariest?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most rewarding: seeing work you’ve done have meaningful impact. Seeing work you’ve done get the results they were designed to have. Being able to work with people you admire and respect, whether it’s clients, companies, people in the industry or your friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scariest: taxes. Going back to the drawing board. Brutal honesty. Admitting you were wrong (but fixing your wrongdoings). Standing up for your work. Firing clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are some of the tools and applications that are essential for a small studio?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insert a list of Apple products here. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all seriousness, it’s whatever it takes to make work feel less like work. It’s whatever it takes to make communication easy. Make things easy for the studio and your clients. Bring in tools that are best-in-class and help the studio and the client in making the work be the best that it can be. Break down the walls as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identify the end. Bring whatever means necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To end on a more open-ended note, what’s next for you and Weightshift?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a low-level, we’re ever-excited at the work we keep doing and the people we get to work with. Outside of immediate client work, we’re hoping to introduce a product this year that we hope will help other studios with streamlining part of the work process. We’ve hinted at it before, where it goes by the internal name of Sleeperhold, and we’re finally starting to see some light at the end of the tunnel for an initial release of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a high-level, we’d like to continue keeping the quality of work high and the studio culture engaged and interested. That means we turn work down, but it means we’re happy inside and more importantly, outside of work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Beyond Familiar</title>
   <link href="http://justinkropp.com/2015/09/20/beyond-familiar/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://justinkropp.com/2015/09/20/beyond-familiar</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.offscreenmag.com&quot;&gt;Offscreen Magaine&lt;/a&gt;, Issue &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.offscreenmag.com/issue3*/&quot;&gt;No3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently visited &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chattanooga,_Tennessee&quot;&gt;Chattanooga&lt;/a&gt; in Tennessee. It’s my hometown and a trip there is never easy for me. There is always a point during my visits when I become emotional as slivers of my past — the good and the bad — resurface. There are parts of the city that conjure up memories that I’d rather not revisit: painful breakups, a car accident, and familial drama. But there are also locations that provide an overwhelming source of happiness and fondness — the hundreds of beautiful days I spent outside rock-climbing with friends, the amazing job I had at an outdoor shop during high-school and college, and my first kiss with Erin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While growing up here, the city always felt comfortable and safe. I knew the people and I knew my way around. Getting lost in this place was almost impossible. The city was predictable, and as I grew older and my curiosity stronger, it didn’t offer what I needed: unfamiliarity and opportunities for discovery. My hometown became destined to be just that: my hometown, a place where I grew up. So I did what I needed to do and moved away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my most recent visit home, while wandering through the town and past some of my usual spots, I began to realise not only how my feelings had changed, but how the city itself had changed. I was now an outside observer visiting a place that felt foreign, despite the familiarity. This was not the hometown I knew anymore. This was not that muted city with only one decent coffee shop and a notable population of vagabonds. This town felt alive and vibrant; its pulse youthful&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-gig_city&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-gig_city&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I found myself discovering things to love; things I hadn’t encountered before. These discoveries were nourishing and restoring my relationship with the place that I once couldn’t wait to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of us, there’s a period in our adolescence when we can’t wait to leave home. We yearn to strike out on our own, carve our own path, and prove that we belong in this world. We need to test ourselves, to prove that we can provide for ourselves and accomplish something. Leaving home is never easy. Change, in general, is never easy, but it’s necessary if we’re to allow ourselves the chance to grow. I’m reminded of a quote by Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr. who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”A mind that is stretched by a new experience can never go back to its old dimensions”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find a lot of parallels between the experiences I’ve had returning home and the relationship I have with our industry. I love what I do and find comfort in knowing that discoveries in technology will continue to push the boundaries of what we do and how we do it. I count myself lucky to be engaged in a creative pursuit that rewards curiosity. But I still get burnt out, run down, and frustrated. Our work not only demands innovative thinking with a pragmatic approach, but managing clients, project budgets, growing to-do lists, and the elusive inbox zero. Our field is evolving at an ever-increasing pace, and if we want to remain relevant we, too, must evolve right along with it. As a digital product designer, change is a responsibility I owe not only myself, but the audiences my work serves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, over the years I’ve learned that professional growth isn’t just about remaining abreast of the advances in our field. Keeping up with the changes in our profession is necessary, but in the process, it is all too easy to close ourselves off in an echo-chamber of design and technology. Sometimes we need to step away from our professional roles and pursue other interests in order to grow. Experiences we have outside the realm of our expertise can help us to provide additional layers of insight to the projects we take on. Our work may become better as a result and provide new perspectives to those who see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had always been interested in psychology, so several years ago I began pursuing a degree in behavioural psychology. I was presented with fascinating facts about the way we behave and the influencers of that behaviour. Entering an unknown territory and engaging with an entirely new subject matter helped me become a better user experience designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left home and gained a new perspective on why I loved where I was from. Stepping away and leaving the familiar behind, if only for a short period of time, can help us broaden our horizons. A renewed vision brings with it a restored focus. We can return to work with a deeper respect for what we do and who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-gig_city&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chattanooga has recently seen a resurgance of a growing wave ofentrepreneurialism, thanks in part to the presence of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thegigtank.com/&quot;&gt;gig-speed internet infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-gig_city&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Rob Giampietro</title>
   <link href="http://justinkropp.com/2015/09/12/rob-giampietro/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://justinkropp.com/2015/09/12/rob-giampietro</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rob-giampietro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rob Giampietro&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This interview was originally published on the now defunct oneskinnyj.com&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-sample_footnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-sample_footnote&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; site. I’m proud of this interview and am grateful to Rob for being so generous with his time and answers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hi Rob. Can you give our viewers a bit of history about yourself (where you went to school, where you’ve worked, and where you are now)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Minneapolis listening to a lot of jazz on ECM and going to the Walker Art Center whenever I could. Minneapolis, ECM, and the Walker’s design department and bookstore were all huge influences on me. I got a B.A. in Art from Yale and went to work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aiga.org/medalists-william-drenttel-and-jessica-helfand/&quot;&gt;Winterhouse&lt;/a&gt;. Bill Drenttel and Jessica Helfand were very giving and had unique practice that allowed me space to develop as a designer — it was like a kind of grad school for me. When I left to go to New York I worked at the New York Times Magazine for almost a year — a great introduction to New York — before I joined Michael Bierut’s team at Pentagram as a freelancer, which was also an amazing learning experience. When my Winterhouse colleague Kevin Smith arrived in New York we began freelancing together and launched the studio Giampietro+Smith, which we ran for five years. I joined &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.projectprojects.com/&quot;&gt;Project Projects&lt;/a&gt; as a principal in 2010. Also in the mix I did a lot of design writing, was vice president of AIGA/NY, did a lot of teaching at Parsons, RISD, and SVA, and started a website of design writing and resources called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linedandunlined.com/&quot;&gt;Lined &amp;amp; Unlined&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve had quite a distinguished career, working at places like Winterhouse, Pentagram and now Project Projects. Were those positions ones that you actively sought after, or did any of them more or less fall into place naturally—one leading to the next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thankful for the opportunities I’ve had. Any career is a mix of skill, luck, and persistence, and I’ve relied on all three. A few ideas have served as helpful guides: 1) actively engage people and places that are interesting to me, 2) cultivate and expand my interests not just as a designer but as a person in the world, and 3) be open to whatever opportunities presented themselves without predetermining their outcomes too much. When I first moved to the city, I showed my portfolio to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pentagram.com/partners/#/15/&quot;&gt;Abbott Miller&lt;/a&gt;, whose work I’d long admired. I was hoping for a job working for him, but he surprised me by saying, “Have you ever thought about teaching? You’d be great.” He introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tdc.org/officers/charles-nix/&quot;&gt;Charles Nix&lt;/a&gt; at Parsons and I taught there for the next 8 years. I was 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why graphic design? I mean, why not something else? What opportunities does graphic design provide that you feel so compelled to engage in this profession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design’s such a pliable profession — there’s a tremendous amount you can do under the umbrella of design, and that was always enticing to me. I love the idea of making things that reach many people. I love the social aspect of being a designer: meeting many different kinds of people, engaging my curiosities and passions. I love language and I am a deeply systematic and analytical person in both my design and my writing. And I have a longstanding fascination with typography — it seems to sit in the valley between language and form, and I like to hang out there too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On your blog, Lined &amp;amp; Unlined, you write quite critically on a range of interests—design, film, poetry, pedagogy. How does writing influence your design practice? Is it an essential part of the process?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing plays many roles. It lets me reflect on practice much the same way teaching does, and it also lets me advocate for ideas, work, and people I think are important and innovative within the profession. At the same time it creates a space outside daily practice — writing for me often happens at night and on weekends — to develop and explore ideas. Often the best way to find out what I think about something is to write about it. There’s this assumption that you must know about something to write about it, but often the process of writing about something mirrors the process of learning about it. Certain pieces I write I know will be key pieces, but other shorter writing is almost like a gym workout — it keeps my mind sharp and my eyes open. I’m not sure that writing’s essential for me. Sometimes it’s addictive and sometimes it’s exhausting. It’s almost always rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you become involved with David Reinfurt, Stuart Bailey, and Dot Dot Dot?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Elliman, whose writing and typographic work I admired before I arrived at Yale, is probably the common link. David was a the T.A. for a class I took with Paul, and it was also during that semester that Stuart came to town and Paul suggested we meet for coffee. We all stayed in touch. I mailed away for the first &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dot-dot-dot.us/&quot;&gt;Dot Dot Dot&lt;/a&gt; and it came with a kind note from Stuart inviting me to contribute to a future issue. They’re my favorite people to write for, everything I’ve done with them is something I’m proud of. They create a very special environment for ideas to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For many designers—and I’d imagine for many other professionals—the act of writing is approached with caution, even fear. Can you talk a little bit about your process for writing (how you approach it)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like anything, you get better at it the more you do it. This is why the blog and doing shorter written pieces is important. Every piece I’ve done has developed a little differently, but just like design it works best for me when there’s a collaboration — in this case, between myself and the editor of the piece. This is why David and Stuart are so important in the writing I’ve done for Dot Dot Dot. We discuss different approaches, references, send things back-and-forth over a few weeks or even months. Then at a certain point it’s time to start writing. Often I have a lot of fragments, sentences or phrasings I like. I also try to have a pool of quotes or quick section outlines floating around in different text windows. The writing almost starts to get “laid out” like a piece of design in this way. I think confidence also builds the more you write, which helps with the fear you have when you start a new piece. I place a huge amount of trust in my ear, the way the language sounds. I’ve rewritten pieces that were fine language-wise but didn’t sound good to my ear — that’s the poet in me I guess. I wrote a Dot Dot Dot piece about the 100th Chapter of Robert Musil’s book &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1MjG19R&quot;&gt;The Man Without Qualities&lt;/a&gt;, and I knew I wanted the piece to end with the biographical image of Musil getting kicked out of the library for smoking, a habit which lead to his early death and left the novel unfinished. I must have rewritten the last paragraph 60 times before I finally got it to sound right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do words and language influence your design work? At any point does semiotic theory become part of the framework for developing a concept? Further, if semiotic theory does play a role, do you find yourself subscribing to any particular tradition—Saussurean or Peircean?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words influence me a great deal, though I don’t think about language in terms of semiotics all that often. I’m very familiar with Saussure and studied him as part of my introduction to literary theory; less so with Pierce but I was just reading up on him now and enjoyed the brief introduction I found — I’m fascinated by the different attributes and aspects of language, especially paradoxes, and in the thinking they reveal. I love some of language’s more formal and sensory qualities. I love the look of language, especially in conceptual art (artists like Lawrence Weiner, Ed Ruscha, John Baldessari, Richard Kostelanetz, Kay Rosen), concrete poetry (poets like Emmett Williams, Dieter Rot, and Eugen Gomringer), along with almost all of Oulipo. I also love the sound of language in more mainstream poetry (poets like Robert Frost, Wallace Stevens, Elizabeth Bishop, Frank O’Hara, and Nicholas Christopher) and contemporary literature (writers like Lydia Davis, Geoff Dyer, Nicholson Baker, and David Means). I like the exploration of genres, modes, reflexivity, and the written text as something that is constructed and allowed to reveal its own construction in order to produce meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying on the same topic of influence, does what you have experienced as a professional practitioner come through in your approach to pedagogy? Are their certain elements to the practice—things that might not be getting addressed in academia—that you believe should have a stronger presence in design education today?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s much like the writing — my practice as a designer feeds my practice as a teacher, and my practice as a teacher in turn gives me ideas and ways of communicating my practice as a designer. They reinforce one another. In terms of where education’s headed, I’ve just finished a long essay that covers design education over the last decade or more, and I think we’re seeing an increased amount of merging between the academic and professional space. In the early ‘90s the design academy was seen as a space that was alternative to practice and its interest was largely theoretical and formally engaged, and there are some for whom it still functions that way. But I think designers increasingly consider school to be part of the production their own professional lives, and they consider learning to be an ongoing and integral process to the development of work and one’s development as a designer. And as a result of this “embeddeness” of the culture of school in everyday design practice, you have more situations where designers are setting up places to learn and exchange ideas — whether it’s conferences, participatory exhibitions, websites, etc. Our own interconnectedness via technology only accelerates and encourages this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;e are living in an increasingly techno-visual culture—where combinations of complex technologies and new visual lexicons are born almost constantly. What is the role of [graphic] design in this new culture and how has the field changed over the last several years? What do you feel has been the most significant shift in the design world within the last five years?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is a reflexive mechanism in culture — it both helps to both set new cultural agendas and reinforce existing ones. The same shifts that have been happening outside the design world for the last five years are helping to shape the most interesting things happening inside design. The more responsive and contextual design can be, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We seem to be in the midst of a shift—a large body of designers moving away from the “client services” aspect of design, and instead pursuing more entrepreneurial endeavors. Do you feel that this is a result of the designer realizing more can be done with that skill, that design can do more than just sell products—it can sell ideologies and philosophy? Or is this shift in behavior a reaction to something larger?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve always seen designers seek opportunities and models for practice outside of commissioned work — whether it was setting up publishing programs, advocating for cultural resistance, building institutions that centralize and reinforce design’s cultural capital, or finding solace in a world of “self-initiated” projects. In many ways, each of these alternative practice models is a product of their times, and the shift to entrepreneurial endeavors you mention is no different. I think we should, as designers, keep inventing more of these as time goes on. But I think as long as design’s central narrative is one of a problem-solving, analytical discipline, then the need and opportunity for service-driven practice will persist and endure. What’s notable, if anything, is the degree to which a ‘90s-era world of self-initiated work has broadened, in the ‘00s, and with the help of the internet, to a world far beyond the self — it’s now a whole design culture, large enough to support the careers of certain designers without the need for them to frame their practices through service. But I’ll sound a cautionary note here: while I think it’s good to launch projects that other designers think are great, I think it’s much more essential that designers look beyond the design sphere in framing new opportunities for themselves. These are the projects — self-initiated, entrepreneurial, commissioned, bartered, speculative, or otherwise — that I look forward to most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s switch gears and round this out with some Project Projects talk: the studio has an enviable portfolio of clients in the arts and architecture sectors and the work always seems to pulse with intellect. Why focus on those sectors? What design opportunities present themselves in these genres that might not in other sectors—like retail or hospitality?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I think there was an appeal in the idea that the arts and architecture represented a intriguingly distinct area of culture from the overtly commercial. While both sectors have clearly commercial aspects and implications, there’s also something intangibly noncommercial about them, something belonging to the world of ideas alone. This created an early set of affinities, both to institutions and to people, which developed into a ready source of projects. As time has passed I think we’ve discovered new and different reasons for our ongoing interest in these sectors. Both art and architecture are “founding disciplines” of graphic design, for example, and as a result share many of the same critical discussions and historical references. And both, as visual and spatial disciplines, have a wealth of aesthetically-motivated individuals who encourage design work that is ambitious and perhaps a bit outside the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top five books a designer must read that have nothing to do with design?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These have both nothing and everything to do with design, which is why designers might enjoy them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark McGurl’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1MjCEji&quot;&gt;The Program Era&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;J.L. Austin’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1FEEaEL&quot;&gt;How to Do Things with Words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Gleick’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1MjCMPN&quot;&gt;The Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lucien Dallenbach’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1FEEfsa&quot;&gt;The Mirror in the Text&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marcel Benabou’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1FEEh3f&quot;&gt;Why I Have Not Written Any of My Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For those designers who are walking down that path to starting their own studio: what advice would you like to impart to them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be fun to come up with 10 of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An untended garden quickly becomes a field: plant what you want to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have partners, but don’t do the same things: make sure you both do something you enjoy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire people for what they can teach you, not for what you can teach them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone should be able to take criticism: creative trust is built on critical honesty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design is only one part of the puzzle: savor the discussion, development, debate, and dissemination of your work just as much as the making of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goals may be arbitrary, but not having them will be maddening when there’s no one else to tell you if you’re doing a good job: set 3-month, 6-month, and 1-year goals at the outset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you take your favorite clients out to lunch, it’s a good time to propose what you’d like to do together next.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowing more designers doesn’t necessarily translate into having good clients: spend your development time wisely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be known for something: it helps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You will never work harder than when you’re building something: find balance. Sometimes the best way to solve a creative problem is to take a vacation or read a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-sample_footnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;oneskinnyj.com was a moniker and online repository I used for several years. It housed the aforementioned interview series, which I will be resurrecting here. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-sample_footnote&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Soul Searching</title>
   <link href="http://justinkropp.com/2015/09/10/soul-searching/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://justinkropp.com/2015/09/10/soul-searching</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I’ve been here — in front of this screen trying to write something. It feels good, I think. I’m not gonna sit here and pretend that my relationship with writing has gotten better, and that that’s why I’m here again. My relationship is the same, but this time I’m a bit more confident. A bit more willing to try and make it work. To get better. To explore thoroughly and output honestly. There’s simply too much going on out there — inside and outside the design field — to quietly ignore. I need a place work it all out. A place that’s public, but still feels safe. Familiar. Comfortable and accepting. Well, accepting may be a bit of a stretch. Anyway, I’m excited about it regardless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site’s got some new skin and guts. They’re both pretty light, as it doesn’t need much. Like most personal sites, expect it to change over time — bit by bit. For now, though, enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
